if you're a beginner to color grading
maybe you're new to final cut pro 10
this is the perfect video for you i'm
going to walk you through
everything you need to know about color
correction and color grading
in final cut pro 10. i'm going to show
you how to use these tools in final cut
pro to make your footage look as good
as possible you gotta just press record
hey guys my name is noel mult with think
media and i'm excited to jump into this
video now there is a difference between
color grading and color correction
most people just call it color grading
which is totally fine but we're gonna
cover both of those
in this video and show you how to do
that to your footage
color grading basically is adding a
stylistic look to your footage to make
it look
cinematic or vibrant something like that
whereas color correction
is kind of fixing the white balance
fixing the exposure the contrast stuff
like that so we're going to cover both
of those things in this video
so let's get right into it now the very
first thing you want to do
inside a final cut pro x is make sure
that your proxies are not
on if you go to this view tab right here
we can see that if we had proxy
preferred or proxy only
then we would want to change that to
optimized original so make sure you just
hit optimized
original and that is going to bring up
your original files
which is going to be best for color
grading you don't want to color grade or
color correct
your proxy files you want to make sure
you have those original files
to color grade with that selected i like
to go to the next step and i like to
open up my scopes kind of get everything
ready for color grading and i'll show
you what those scopes are
if you go up to the view tab you are
going to see video scopes right here you
can also hit command
7 to bring those up and if we click that
we're going to see
these uh colors the red the green the
blue and we're going to change all this
but these things are going to make it a
lot easier for us to color grade
and i'll show you how to use this but
instead of doing this i actually like to
change up my workspace just a little bit
so that
these are as big as possible and the
easiest way to do this
is if you go up here to window you will
see
workspaces and right here there's color
and effects if you pull this up
you are going to see this entire left
side just go away and this is going to
make everything nice and big for you
perfect for color grading and color
correcting so this is a very nice
workspace that you can use
if you are color grading and if you want
to change that back maybe you're ready
to go back
uh to the edit what you can do is go up
to window hover over workspaces and you
can go back to default and this is going
to put it back
just how you had it so going back to my
workspaces going to color and effects
i actually don't need all four of these
so what i like to do is go up here to
view
and then i'm going to change this just
to two one on top one on bottom now this
is looking great and if you want to use
it like this which is how i use it
you can go back up to window you can go
to workspaces you can actually
save this workspace we'll just call it
color grading which i already have mine
saved
as color grading but if you hit save
this is going to save this workspace for
you
so that you don't have to go in and mess
with this every time you just go to
window
workspace now when you hit color grading
it is going to pull this up
how you like it now if you're a beginner
and you're just learning how to color
grade the odds are you don't really have
a flat
log image which would look something
like this
right here this is a flat image or what
they would call
a log image the odds are you're shooting
some videos on your standard picture
profile on your camera now that's
totally fine you can still mess with
these colors
and i'm gonna show you how to do that
that's why i have some footage here
where it's a bit colored already
this is just the standard picture
profile on the sony zv1
and i have some different clips here
that we're going to look at this one
right here with my face in it show you
how to kind of color
when there are some skin tones in there
as well as just some random
shots here with a lot of different
greens and blues different colors to
mess around with now something you want
to get familiar with
is your color inspector what you can do
is hit the color board right here and if
you drag this
onto your clip in this inspector right
here you are going to see a color board
and you can open that up
and from here you can make some
adjustments but i actually
do not like to use the color board now
instead of doing that this is actually a
shortcut as well you can just click
on this little color inspector triangle
right here and this is going to pull up
the same thing for you but this is
actually called the color wheels now
odds are if you click on that it's going
to pull up your color board
to change that just go into final cut
pro go to preferences and right here
under general we can see color
correction and it's going to be set onto
color board just naturally but we want
to set this
to color wheels with that selected we
can exit out of that
now you can see when you click on this
triangle it's just going to pull up your
color wheels
right here let's start by taking a look
at these four wheels and what they do
and how they can affect your image this
top wheel right here is our master wheel
so this is going to affect
everything we have shadows mid-tones and
highlights but the master is going to
affect
all of those all three shadow mid tones
and highlights now the left side of the
wheel
is our saturation you can see it's a bit
more blue up here and it's a bit more
faded out down here that lets you know
that it is the saturation so as we go up
this is going to make things a lot more
saturated you can see
how much more vibrant this image is and
if i bring it all the way down you can
see that it's going to turn to black and
white
there is no saturation to these colors
now each wheel kind of has the same
layout on the left side you are going to
have that saturation so let's go to
shadows and if i pull those all the way
down you're gonna see that the shadows
are now black and white but we still
have some mid-tones and highlights a lot
of these blues
still have some color now back up here
on master the right side of the wheel is
going to be our exposure you can see up
here it's a bit brighter
down here it's darker so as we increase
the master
it's going to make everything much
brighter starting to blow out some of
our image
doesn't look the best but as we darken
it this is going to darken
our entire image make everything a lot
darker now right here in the center we
can actually move
this little point around and this is
going to add color
into our entire shot so if i drag this
up into the magenta
it's going to make everything a bit more
magenta i can do the same if i want to
pull that into the green
or i want to make it warmer make it a
bit orange you can do that by dragging
these around
in each of these wheels now real quick
i'm just going to throw these all around
i'm going to show you how to
reset these if you ever need to so let's
say you want to reset
all of it all you have to do is click on
this little reset button
and that is going to bring everything
back to normal for this one wheel
but let's say you don't want to bring
everything back you just want to bring
back
maybe this piece right here if you
double click that is going to bring back
just that property i can do the same
with the saturation by double clicking
it's going to bring it back double
clicking going to bring it back so
that's how you can kind of reset some of
these values
as you are going through your color
grade like i mentioned these are gonna
work the same as the master however this
is only going to affect
your shadows this is only going to
affect your highlights this is only
going to affect your mid tones and so
you can mess with each of these by only
affecting you know a specific part of
your shot
after i show you what all of these do
i'm gonna walk you through exactly how i
color correct and color grade a shot
so stick with me we're almost there
these are the things that you need to
know before you start
color correcting down here we have
temperature tint and hue now
this was shot on auto white balance on
the sony zv1 but if you mess up your
white balance this is where you could
fix
some of those issues by sliding these
around so this temperature if you drag
it to the right
this number is going to increase and
that is going to increase
the warmth of your shot and the tint is
going to increase in
magenta as you pull it to the right and
as you pull it to the left it is going
to add
green to your shot if you pull the
temperature left it's going to be cooler
and adding that blue tone
to your shot messing with the hue is
going to adjust all of your colors
and kind of swing them around on your
colors wheel making it look a bit funky
this is not something that i
ever use but maybe if you're shooting a
music video or you know there might be
an instance where you would use this
this is where you can mess with the hue
down here under mix i usually just leave
at 1 but if you want to dial it back so
that it's not at 100
strength it's kind of like the opacity
of this effect you can drag this to the
left
and zero you can see that there is
nothing happening and to the right you
can see this is
with everything applied i usually leave
this at one and i just dial everything
in
exactly how i want it but that is there
if you ever want to dial
it back and forth you can do that if you
also want to see kind of the before and
after
what you can do is uncheck this box and
this is going to
disable it and then if you check it
again it's going to bring it back now
that you know what these wheels do let's
actually color correct and color grade
this image to look a bit better a bit
more vibrant maybe a bit more summery
but first we want to take a look at
these scopes over here now these might
be a bit intimidating but i promise you
it's really easy if you just take the
time
and understand what these are it's going
to help you so much right now we're just
going to ignore
this vector scope which is this circle
up here
and we are gonna kind of save that for
our part two of this video which is
gonna be a bit more advanced where i'm
gonna cover stuff
like luts you know film simulations
adjustment layers grading log
images getting correct skin tone stuff
like that is gonna be an
advanced tutorial where i will use the
spectroscope once that part 2 advanced
tutorial comes out
make sure you check that out because
you're going to learn so much more but
you definitely need to watch this video
first because this is going to lay down
the foundations of color correcting and
color grading so that you're not
completely
lost when it comes to the advanced
tutorial but for now we're just going to
focus on this waveform down here
which is our luma waveform now if you
ever want to change these you can click
on this right here and change this from
luma sometimes i use the rgb
overlay now this waveform right here is
actually showing us the
values in this shot so as i move this
around you're gonna see
this also moves because this is showing
us exactly
what is on screen and it's showing us
the brightness
of the shot now on this waveform we have
some numbers the main thing that you
want to look at
is this 100 number if you go above this
line
you are gonna start losing information
in your shot so for example if we
go to our highlights and we boost these
highlights you can see that the entire
graph is now moving up
because it's showing us the brightness
of the shot so as i move these
highlights
above a hundred you are going to see
that the sky is starting to lose
a lot of its color it just is white now
because it is over
this 100 line so you want to try and
keep things that you want to have color
things that you want to be in the shot
below that 100 line
this is the same with the shadows as i
start to decrease the shadows we are
going below
this zero line and that means that we
are losing color and details
in the shadows it's starting to take
colors and just make them
black so typically you want most your
colors to be
above zero and below 100.
as i move these mid-tones you are going
to see that the waveform kind of
scrunches upwards or if i move it down
it's starting to scrunch
downwards and i really use mid-tones for
adding contrast so let's go to this shot
right here and i'm going to color
correct and color gray this a bit
exactly how i would do this for my own
video
first things first you want to make sure
you have that clip selected and then we
can start making
our adjustments now when looking at the
shot one of the things i want to fix
is how dark it is around my face because
it's a bit too
contrasty for me and so first thing that
i would do is go over to my mid-tones
and on this right side we have that
exposure
and i'm just going to increase this to
bring some of that life back
into those mid-tones so we can see
what's going on in the shadows now when
i did that you can see that i actually
lifted this entire thing up so even
though i was just messing with the
mid-tones the shadows were a bit
affected as well
and i still want contrast in this shot
so what i'll do is i will take
my shadows and i'm going to bring those
down just to the bottom of this graph to
see how this
looks so far that's looking pretty good
i'm going to mess with my highlights see
if i want to bring those down or
up but honestly where they're at is
pretty good you know everything's at the
top
of this 100 and so far i'm happy with
how this looks if i click this
on and off you can see how much we
really brought back
into the face how much we brought back
into the shot just by adjusting those
mid-tones up and then bringing the
shadows back down to keep the contrast
but also bring life to those shadows
when it comes to adding saturation i
like to use the master wheel so it
affects the entire shot so i'm just
going to increase it
just a hair now that i'm liking how this
looks i kind of want to give this a warm
summer vibe and so we're going to mess
with some of the colors add a bit of
warmth into this shot first i'm going to
start with the temperature and just kind
of increase this and see what this looks
like and you can see as i increase the
warmth it gets a bit
green as well so i'm going to grab the
tint and i'm going to bring it this way
to add
some magenta back into this shot now the
highlights i'm just going to add
some warmth to this by dragging it
towards these oranges
and now my skin is getting a bit too
orange and so what i'll do is i'll go to
my mid tones i'm going to pull it in the
opposite direction
adding a bit of blue to the midtones i'm
also going to add a little bit of blue
into the shadows and maybe increase my
highlights even more
i'm also gonna bring my highlights down
just the hair now this is definitely
more of a stylized shot
everything is a bit warmer it looks very
summery
very warm and so if i click this on and
off you can see the before and after
is pretty crazy right look how dark this
is it looks really cool
it looks natural but when i click this
on everything is much warmer the shadows
have been lifted and i like the warmth
that we're getting in the sky
and those greens i think it looks really
awesome when it comes to color grading
there's no correct way to do it it
definitely is just finessing in the
colors
messing with it it takes a while to
figure out you know where you want your
colors in the shadows
the mid-tones the highlights and so
practice just start messing with shots
there is no wrong way to do this just
start messing around with it see how it
looks
and you'll get better over time now i'm
going to show you a really cool trick
that you can do here in final cut but
first let's copy over these effects
command c
we're going to paste them onto this by
hitting option command v
now we can see that it copied everything
over but it's not
looking too good so i'm gonna go back
into my color wheels and make a few
adjustments to the exposure i think it
looks a little bit flat so we're gonna
add a little more contrast
to the shot
that's looking a bit better i kind of
like having the highlights a bit lower i
think it looks really cool
for this shot
okay now that i like how this is looking
looks very warm very cinematic what i'm
going to do
is actually add in a new thing by
clicking up this down arrow right here
we're going to add in our hue saturation
curves
now in this video we're just going to
take a look at these top three the
hubers hue
the huber sat and the hubris luma i'm
gonna show you what these do
and how they can really affect your
image if we click this eyedropper right
here on hue vs hue
i can select any color i want and it is
going to show me what color it is right
here
and as i drag this up and down it's
actually going to mess with that color
specifically so it's not going to mess
with the hue on all the colors like that
one little hue wheel did
this is going to mess with just that one
color so if i want to make that blue
water
a bit more blue i can drag it down like
this and it's going to add in
some more blues and just change the hue
of what the pool originally was
i'm also going to do this with the green
so if i click
on this little green right here there's
some different colors in this tree so
like this is going to be a little bit
different
than say this green back here you can
see the screen has a lot more blue in it
but i want to mess with these colors
right here so as i drag these down
they can get really bizarre really blue
and you can mess with these and kind of
fine tune
exactly the look that you're going for
let's say i'm really liking this shot
but i think
the blue in the pool is just a bit too
saturated i like the color i just want
it less saturated this is what the
huever sat is for so if you click
the eyedropper and then select the pool
color
from here if you drag it down you can
desaturate the pool
and if you drag it up it is just going
to increase
the saturation so i'm going to keep it
right about there and i'm going to do
the same thing with these trees because
the green is a really cool green i just
do not like how saturated it is
okay now this is looking really cool so
if i turn this off you can see what this
looks like before
and then i turn it on this is what it
looks like after so this is where you
can get
really creative and really stylize a
look and color grade
using this hue saturation curves is a
really fun tool
just to mess around with the colors and
make something that is really unique
now that i really like this look i'm
going to copy and paste this image onto
a new video so so far it looks pretty
good but i'm going to show you guys
actually the main reason why i use the
hue saturation curves
and it's typically with skin tones and
kind of decreasing maybe some of the
redness in the skin
or if the skin is just too saturated
bringing that saturation down just a
little bit and i basically use this in
almost every single think media video
and what i do is i go into the huber
saturation
use that eyedropper i select the skin
and then this allows me to really
refine that saturation in the skin tone
so if i want to bring it down just a
hair i can and usually the redness you
know on my cheeks or my nose sometimes
can just get a little bit
too red when i add in saturation and so
i can click on my cheeks
or my nose and maybe bring you know this
area down a little bit you can see that
the lips now have no color
and so i just bring it back up until i
think it has a good enough
saturation but not too much this is
before any of the hue saturation curves
and this is
after the hue saturation curves this is
before the entire
image and this is after click on the
screen to watch another final cut pro 10
tutorial or you can click on the bottom
screen if you want to watch our advanced
part 2 color grading video i'll see you
guys in the next video
you